if a 60% free throw shooter takes 10
shots what is the probability that it
makes exactly seven of them
to answer questions like that we can use
this formula for the binomial
distribution and this doesn't just apply
to free throws it applies whenever
there's a repeating process where you
could put the outcomes into two
categories that's where the buy and
binomial comes from and that kind of
situation is pretty common considering
it encompasses all yes or no questions
the formula looks a bit scary but by the
end of this video we'll make sense of it
and hopefully it's pretty along the way
[Music]
okay we're going to start with one blob
it's programmed to make it 60 of the
time so what's the probability that it
would make one out of one this question
feels a little bit silly we don't need
any fancy formulas to know that the
answer is sixty percent but it's a
starting point to build on another silly
starting question is what's the
probability it makes zero of one it's
the other forty percent of the time
sixty percent is the same as three out
of five so we can visualize the
probabilities by looking at five blobs
and having three of them make it and two
of them Miss
okay now what if the blobs take two
shots each it'll be helpful to have more
blobs to look at here so let's make this
into a square of blobs and have the new
blobs also take their first shot again
with three out of five of them making it
and then they can all take a second shot
which means we now have to ask about
making zero one or two of two shots you
might notice this isn't exactly random
but for the moment we're just focusing
on making a clean diagram
four of the 25 blobs were unlucky enough
to miss both the first and the second
shot from this we can say that a sixty
percent free throw shooter has a 16
probability of missing both shots and
this is the same number we would have
gotten by multiplying the probabilities
of the individual shot outcomes the
probability of missing the first shot is
40 then 40 percent of those forty
percent also missed the second shot and
forty percent of forty percent comes out
to sixteen percent next for the blobs
that made one shot we have two groups
one group of six made the first and
missed the second shot and six out of 25
is 24 again we can multiply the
individual probabilities to check that
they come out the same and indeed sixty
percent for the make times forty percent
for the Miss comes out to twenty four
percent the second group is pretty much
the same except the make and the Miss
come in the opposite order
and adding these together we get a 48
probability for making one or two shots
and for the ones that made both shots
there's again just one group and we can
fill in the numbers in the same way and
all these probabilities add up to 100
which is a great sign
we're gonna add a third shot in a moment
here but it might already be possible to
guess at the pattern so try pausing and
see if you can predict what it's going
to look like after three shots
okay for the third shot it'll be useful
to have even more blobs to look at so
let's make this a 3D grid and have the
new blobs take their first two shots
[Music]
with three shots the top three layers
made it and the bottom two layers missed
it's a little bit difficult to see
what's going on inside this Cube so
let's pull it apart into sections and
organize it by outcome okay so again
there's only one way to miss all of the
shots eight of the 125 blobs ended up in
this category which gives us a
probability of 6.4 percent for that
outcome and again we could get this same
number by multiplying the probabilities
of the individual misses
next for one make out of three shots
there are three ways to get it the first
way in this list is Miss Miss then make
12 of the 125 blobs had this outcome
which gives us a 9.6 probability
multiplying the individual probabilities
looks like this
the thing to notice here is that all
three of these groups have the same
number of blobs in them the probability
is the same for each of them we don't
care about the order of makes and misses
we just care about how many there are
and Order also doesn't matter for
multiplication so each of these comes
out to the same 9.6 percent which means
we don't have to go through all the
different ways of making one of three we
can just calculate the probability for
one of them then multiply that result by
3 to get the overall probability of
making one out of three shots
and this idea will come in handy for
looking at two out of three just like
before there are three groups and they
each have the same probability which is
14.4 percent each for an overall
probability of 43.2 percent to make two
out of three and four three out of three
there's just one way with a probability
of 21.6 percent
so we have this pattern of counting the
number of specific ways to make a
certain number of shots and then
multiplying that by the probability for
each of those specific ways which again
are always the same and that's exactly
what this formula does this bit here
stands for the number of ways to get K
makes out of n total shots it's called
the binomial coefficient in this example
we just went through the binomial
coefficient is one three three or one
depending how many makes we're asking
about we don't yet have a great way of
finding it for other numbers of attempts
and makes so most of the rest of this
video is going to focus on that and the
second part is multiplying the
probabilities of the individual shots
this little p is the probability of a
success so 60 in this case and one minus
the little p is the probability of a
failure so forty percent and if we write
these calculations so far using
exponents you can start to see how they
have the same shape as the formula so
this formula has a lot of pieces and a
lot of letters so depending how much
practice you've had with algebra
recently it might feel a bit
overwhelming if so I can guarantee
you're not alone and it might be a good
exercise to pause take out a piece of
paper and plug the numbers into the
formula for each case yourself
now all the math nerds out there are
going to yell at me with good reason if
I don't mention that this formula only
makes sense if the shots are independent
of each other which might not be true
for example missing the first shot might
make you nervous changing the
probability of making the next shot
making things way more complicated for
the rest of this video though we're
going to assume that the interactions
between shots are minor enough that we
can ignore them and these blobs don't
even have the memory of a goldfish so
every shot is a fresh start that might
sound lazy but even if you care about
making the most accurate model possible
it's usually good to start with a
simpler model then test it to see how it
performs then add complexity if you need
to
alright so now we have the overall
structure of the formula figured out but
we're not quite ready to answer that
original question about making seven of
ten shots
we can plug in the numbers but it's not
clear just yet how we count how many
different ways there are to arrange
seven makes and three misses
okay let's start fresh forgetting about
the probabilities and just focus on
Counting the ways each number of shots
could be made which again is called the
binomial coefficient starting with a
blob that hasn't taken any shots yet
there's only one possibility where it's
made zero shots when the blob takes a
shot there are two possible branches
reality can take one where the shot goes
in and one where the shot misses and
this is true every time we add a shot
for the second shot these two
possibilities split into four
possibilities one possible way of
missing both shots two possible ways of
making one of the two and one way of
making both so just like before we have
this one two one pattern after two shots
the neat thing about this table is that
both ways to make one out of two shots
are tracked together the tree of blobs
over on the right tracks every single
possible order of makes and misses but
the number of blobs we have to draw is
going to double every time we add a shot
since we only care about the total
number of makes lumping them together in
a table is good enough and it makes the
tracking a lot easier
and adding a third shot we get the same
pattern we found before with one three
three and one ways to get each total of
successes but now it's going to be a lot
easier to add a fourth shot we can just
continue the pattern of pushing the
numbers down the table and combining
them so for four shots it looks like
there's still just one way to miss them
all four ways to make one six ways to
make two four ways to make three and one
way to make all four and we can just
continue this pattern to find any number
we need
so now we could use the binomial
distribution formula to answer this
question from the very beginning of the
video what is the probability a sixty
percent free throw shooter will make
seven of ten we can look at this table
to see that there are 120 ways to make 7
out of 10 shots
and the probability for each of those
ways happening is 0.6 to the seventh
power for the seven makes times 0.4 to
the third power for the three misses
that comes out to a pretty small number
but if you combine all 120 different
ways to make seven they add up to about
21.5 percent so that's our answer
this pattern is known as Pascal's
triangle it's usually written like this
the numbers on the outside of each row
are one and each number in the middle is
found by adding the two numbers above it
so we now have a way to get this
binomial coefficient for any numbers but
it's still a lot of work especially if
the numbers are big so it would be nice
if there were a faster way to do it
the good news is there's a formula for
the binomial coefficient the bad news is
it looks like this
those exclamation points are called
factorials if you haven't seen them
before I think it's easiest to explain
them with examples one factorial is one
two factorial is two times one three
factorial is three times two times one
and four factorial is say it with me
four times three times two times one you
multiply the number by one less than
itself then by two less and so on all
the way down to one so to say this
formula in words we take the factorial
of the total number of shots and then we
divide by the factorial of the number of
makes and we also divide by the
factorial of the number of Misses which
reminds me zero factorial is defined as
one that can feel a bit weird at first
so I'll link to some videos about it but
I figured I should mention it because
it's required for this formula to work
when we have 0 makes or zero misses
anyway with this formula we can find the
binomial coefficient without having to
look at Pascal's triangle but it's
probably not super clear yet why this
formula Works to make sense of it let's
zoom out a bit and think about counting
Arrangements in General we'll start out
with one object how many ways are there
to arrange this one object there's just
one I guess there it is
if we had a second object we can do it
in one of two weights we can put it to
the left or to the right so by adding a
second object we multiply the number of
possible Arrangements by two
to add a third object we can take the
previous orderings one at a time and add
the new objects to three different
places left middle or right so by adding
a third object we multiply the number of
possible Arrangements by three you might
be starting to see a pattern but let's
do one more if we add a fourth object
there are four places we can put it so
by adding a fourth object we multiply
the number of possible Arrangements by
four the number of possible Arrangements
is already starting to get out of hand
but thankfully we can see the pattern
now and don't have to list them all out
anymore if you want to arrange any
unique objects there are n factorial
ways to do it and that's where the N
factorial in the numerator of this
formula comes from now is a good time to
pause and make sure that n factorial in
the numerator make sense if it doesn't
the part that comes next certainly won't
either all that's left is to figure out
the factorials in the bottom of the
formula these let us account for
situations where the objects aren't
unique but instead fall into two
different categories like makes and
misses remember that's what binomial
means we're going to look at some
examples to help this make sense but the
quick explanation is that since we don't
care about the order of identical
objects n factorial is counting
orderings we don't care about so we have
to divide by the number of ways to
arrange the objects in each category so
for example let's focus on the situation
with three blobs and we'll take the
perspective that we only care about
whether the blobs are wearing hats or
not
two of the three blobs are wearing hats
so if we just care about hat or no half
of the orderings are the same half of
them have the wizard hat first and half
of them have the propeller hat first so
we should divide by the two ways of
ordering the two hats or to write it in
a way that looks like the binomial
coefficient formula we could divide by
the two factorial ways to order the two
hats and also the one factorial ways to
order the one blob with no hat this
example has pretty small numbers so the
pattern might not be super clear yet so
let's run through some examples with
four blobs we have four factorial total
ways to arrange the blobs but if we're
just worried about the hats we'll again
divide by the two factorial ways to
order the hats but will also divide by
the two factorial ways to order the
non-hats and this gets us to six
orderings of hats and non-hats okay
let's do one more example this time with
three of the four blobs wearing hats we
still have four factorial ways to
arrange the blobs and focusing on the
hat or not hat orderings we can divide
by the three factorial ways to arrange
the hats which gets us to four for these
examples with small numbers it wouldn't
be too hard to just list out all the
possibilities and count them but this
pattern where we take the factorial of
the total number of objects then divide
by the factorials of the numbers in each
group are focusing on lets us find the
binomial coefficient for any numbers
imagine trying to do this by hand for
the 7 out of 10 example this is just a
small taste of the area of math that
deals with counting how to group or
arrange things which is called
combinatorics so that's something you
could look up if you're interested in
hearing more about this kind of thing
so we've done a bunch of theorizing
about how this formula should be able to
calculate the probabilities of a free
throw shooter hitting a certain number
of shots before we're satisfied with it
though we should check that it works by
testing it against some randomized
results Let's test it with ten thousand
blobs since that's a number that only
almost breaks my computer
[Music]
foreign
it's pretty close it's not exact but we
shouldn't expect it to be exact even
with 10 000 blobs and we did get this
one blob that didn't make a single shot
poor little buddy let's let it keep
trying while we summarize what we've
learned about this formula for
repeatable independent events whose
results can be categorized as a yes or a
no this formula gives the probability
that you get a certain number of yeses
or no's in a certain number of Trials
and of course you need to know the
probability of an individual yes or no
a lot of work goes into these videos and
we're committed to providing them for
free if you happen to be in a position
where you're able to give you can help
us produce more of these videos by
supporting on patreon but even if you're
not able to provide financial support we
appreciate very much that you watched
all the way to the end and we'll see you
next time
foreign